Far from the cities and the polls, Fort
Calquier, a beautiful village in Provence
dear to Jionau and Pagnol.  Every
Sunday, around a hundred parishioners
attend the 10:30 am high mass while
the majority of the fortified people of Calceria
prepare for another cult, that of the PMU.
That morning, like all French people
since the beginning of the war, they
heard the latest news.  The
United States rejected [music] the
Soviet peace plan, and everyone is
asking: "When will the land war break out
?" We are four
days away from the ceasefire. In the square,
in the cafes, and even in church, the
conflict engulfing the Middle East is
on everyone's mind.
When you see all this suffering, don't forget
that most of our
misfortunes, the misfortunes of humankind, stem
from our freedom.
War, for example, and it is not
God's will to wage war,
it is the will of humankind. And then, of course, there are
all these misfortunes, all
this suffering that breaks the
hearts of men, and for which we bear no responsibility
. The suffering of a child, the death
of an innocent, the suffering of mothers
who lose their sons.
After Mass, the parishioners
linger on the church steps to chat. It's a
far cry from golf. The conversations
revolve more around spring,
which has arrived early.
In the bistros surrounding the square, one  He
makes his predictions not on the outcome
of the conflict but on the
afternoon's trifecta. Since the invasion of Kouit on
August 2nd, nothing has changed in the
habits of Fort Calquier except for
the tone of the jokes aimed at the North
Africans living here.
golf they're going to send you
no but
you someone don't know him
huh
he's going to you someone you don't know yeah
that's true but how
can you no longer garage
no but how can you be
poster glue for the green and too lady at the
same time
how do you manage to do he's right he's right there
you'll see my part
who you'll see
because now that it's started you don't really know what they're going to
use it's a pledge and
land war or not you must above all not
miss the closing time of the
bets because the trifecta is a
serious matter. Only then do we want to
talk about golf
[grunt] did
n't want the p now we kill him.
There you go. I don't know the big one  The problem
we might have with them is that
it could trigger something in
this world. That's the problem,
that's it. Besides, he
sought to
completely disunite the United Nations
because it's a demolition.
What did he do? He made people
believe whatever he wanted. He leads them wherever
he wants with religion and that's it
. It's not like you, you're going to say
tomorrow, it's not true,
and then I say, last night he held firm,
but he's right, and he's right, and I agree with him, like he
said, it's like the guy who
says we're doing a transplant because we don't want to
load the containers, the others are
busting their asses, I take them, I
put them in bulk in the truck, I carry them to the truck, what do
you think, it's not logical, you know, I do
n't know, you see, I'm
going to tell you, at
their place over there,  He couldn't have
attacked them with tanks, he could have attacked them
with pigs.
But he's right, he's right.
You let the pigs loose. I think that's all over
.
No, but that's how it is.
And the pigs
and the pin-ups, hair. But then that's
another thing, another thing.
Whatever the
No, what I do
n't approve of there is that we have guys who might get killed, who might get
hurt, you understand? And then
who Why? Why exactly?
Watch out for
all the guys who are B, I have a kid
who stayed 3 months.
Well listen to me, you don't have the right to
alcohol, you don't have the right to women,
you don't have the right to anything at all. You
support the country even friendly countries, I don't like it
. No
no, damn it, I don't know if it's a
dictatorship but you look at Algeria.
You look at Algeria, they had the
Well-being when we were now they're
breaking our hands, it's a pain in the
ass. But where are we going with this? But
where are we going with this? Goddamn it, he's going to mess things up
anyway. No,
yeah. No, but I'm willing to believe
you see there he's going to cut off his
balls the pala
here come here that
she made the p to the Arabs that she left
the Arabs alone yeah
you're bothering
the Arabs how come
after the trifecta the aperitif the
Sunday meal and the nap the unmissable
game of pétanque
to evoke anything other than the distance
between the balls and the pig
how good they are
sun while at
the other end of
Fort Calquier the local team in red
receives the neighboring village
between the applause of the
supporters a throw-in and
a penalty obviously contested. Only one
spectator listens to the latest
news.
How do the vacationers who are on
winter sports right now perceive the
conflict? It's certain, there is a
huge gap. Here in
End of the day, calm returns to
Fort Calquier. The few tourists
return home. Everyone wants to hear
the televised address that
the President of the Republic will deliver at 8 p.m.
Apparently, the situation doesn't accept a
ceasefire; how far will the
Allied troops go? His
objective is clear:
liberation.
So, for a month now, the objective has been to
loosen the lines, to
penetrate
the territory of the colonizer. Not to say
that we have confidence, yeah, that's true,
and in many French homes there are
fathers, mothers, wives,
children who are trembling.
Yes, yes, well, sure, or so we know,
certainly not for the same reasons as
him, but
without exaggerating, surely in your
name too.
Good morning, sir/madam.
Here you are. Would
you like a slice of cooked leg, please?
Yes.
What do you think?
What do we think? We think like
everyone else.
How many hours did you tell me? 6,
especially
Monday morning, market day. At the beginning of
the war, the 300  North Africans didn't dare
leave their homes much, but a few
days later they were back to their old
habits. Here, we live in
harmony. A stop
at the
newsstand is a must. Since the start of the war, there have been
more customers.
I wish life could go on
like everyone else, you know. But anyway, how are
you all doing? I'm afraid
it's going to last a few more days.
Yes. Magazine, huh?
Yes.
We'll see about that later.
I don't know where it is anymore. But anyway
, we had to do
something, don't think so.
Yes,
and thank you.
I think we're there, huh?
How so? Yes,
we know, maybe it won't be
long.
I don't know about that, huh,
huh.
[laughs]
I don't really know.
Well, anyway, we couldn't back down
now, huh?
Yes, that's for sure. Just
because the war is going to stop doesn't mean
the problems
will be solved. So, it's true that,
like the  As the President of the
Republic said, we will still need to sit down
together, we will still need to
think about discussing and quickly
get around a table to resolve
the other problems that have arisen.
Well, notably the Palestinian problem,
the Lebanese problem, the problem of the
occupied territories, right? Uh, it's
true that for
a
lasting period to take hold in these
countries, we will need to sit down together
.
It creates an economic blockage, and this is
an
indirect consequence that has greatly
disrupted people's lives.
A reporter from a community radio station, microphone in hand,
comes to gauge the
public's mood,
and you get the impression that they spoke thoroughly about the ins and outs of the
conflict's origins, the reasons, and
so on. Do you feel well-
informed about all the causes of the conflict
?
At the beginning, we were hearing about it
every day, but now we get
the impression... well, I do
n't know, for me it's a bit... it's a bit...
Less complete than at the beginning, when now it's
unthinkable.
We're at the end of the 20th century and we're
still having wars.
Well, I thought that because we
were in the 20th century and
soon the 21st, there wouldn't be any more wars like
that, because I'm
old enough to have lived through the
Algerian War.
Yes. And I thought it was the
last one, as our fathers and grandfathers probably thought when
they lived through theirs. So
I didn't think we'd be crazy enough
to use such methods, and
especially what's happening
now, it seems to me, is a bit like the
hunter and the hunted. When the hunter
takes his rifle, when he goes up
into the hills, he says, well, it's
certain that the hare,
or the woodcock, won't get me. And right now
, that's a bit what's happening
with the Americans.  That is to say,
carpet bombing is being done,
houses are being destroyed, there are undoubtedly many more
deaths than are being acknowledged
.
And right now, it's certain that it
will leave scars,
deep scars. I don't know what
you think.
I hope it won't affect
people's consciences so that they
become
racist or whatever. Now, that's
the problem. That's what the
scars are.
We have to see
what the consequences will be after the
war because right now, that's what
the scars are.
We risk seeing a radicalization of the
Muslim world, at the level of fundamentalists,
for example.
And fundamentalism is bad in
every sense of the word, on both the
Muslim and Catholic sides.
They are prisoners; they can no
longer fight anyone.
Clearly, racism is not on the
rise. The
Gulf War has not succeeded in shaking the
peace.  of its inhabitants. Today, with
the war over, more
than ever the Calcerian forts will be
able to resume habits barely disrupted
by 7 months of conflict.